A Guide to the J. William Jones Papers, 1861-1892
Library of Virginia
Library of Virginia
J. William Jones Papers, 1861-1892
Library of Virginia
21294
28 leaves, negative photostats
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection is open to research.
Acquisition Information
Lent for copying by William S. Jones of Tazewell, Virginia, 1938.
Biographical Information
John William Jones was born 25 September 1836 in Louisa County, Virginia, to Francis Willian Jones and Ann Pendleton Ashby Jones. Jones attended the University of Virginia, graduating in 1859, then attended the Southern Baptist Theological Seminary in Greenville, South Carolina. Ordained in 1860, he returned to Louisa County to preach at Little River Baptist Church. When the Civil War began, he enlisted as a private in the 13th Virginia Regiment, then became regimental chaplain, then a missionary chaplain to the army. Jones conducted revivals in the army throughout the war. After the Civil War ended, he preached at the Baptist Church in Lexington, Virginia, and was chaplain at Washington College (now Washington and Lee University). He served churches in Ashland, Virginia, and Chapel Hill, North Carolina, as well as serving as chaplain at the University of Virginia and the University of North Carolina. He was the secretary of the Southern Historical Society from 1875 to 1887, and he edited and wrote several works on the war and on Robert E. Lee. Jones was chaplain-general of the United Confederate Veterans from 1890 to 1909. Jones married Judith Page Helm in December 1860, and they had five children. Jones died in Columbus, Georgia, 17 March 1909.
Scope and Content
Papers, 1861-1892, of J. William Jones (1836-1909) of Richmond, Virginia consisting of correspondence to Jones in his capacity as secretary of the Southern Historical Society, and discussing aspects of the war and the business of the society. Papers contain letters, 1876-1888, from Jefferson Davis (1808-1889) of New Orleans, Louisiana, and Beauvoir, Mississippi, discussing rhetorical attacks on the post-war South, the assassination of Abraham Lincoln (1809-1865), his role in the unveiling of a statue of Robert E. Lee (1807-1870), and prohibition in the 1880s. Papers consist of letters, 1879-1887, from Fitzhugh Lee (1835- 1905) discussing letters, the Southern Historical Society, a dispute with the society over speaker's fees, and request for a Jefferson Davis autograph by H. Douglas Lee of New York passed on from Fitzhugh Lee to Jones. Papers also include two letters, 1867 and n.d., from John B. Gordon (1832-1904) requesting information on Civil War campaigns and agreeing to write a letter of introduction. Papers contain letter, 8 February 1875, from Joseph E. Johnston (1807-1891) concerning his relationship with Robert E. Lee and correspondence, 1885, from Johnston and Robert Stiles (1836-1905) concerning the battle reports for the battle of Seven Pines (Fair Oaks) in 1862. Papers also contain a letter, 6 August 1876, from John B. Hood (1831-1879) asking for a review to be sent to him and a letter, 30 August 1892, from Thomas Nelson Page (1853- 1922) thanking Jones for comments on his writings. Also include a letter, 30 November 1861, from John C. Breckenridge (1821-1875) of the 1st Kentucky Brigade to Colonel Charles Dimmock (1800-1863), chief of ordnance, thanking him for muskets sent for the regiment and a letter, n.d., from General Winfield Scott (1786-1866) to Major E. Johnson (1816-1873) inviting him to dinner.
Arrangement
Arranged chronologically.
Contents List
- Letter, 30 November 1861, John C. Breckinridge, headquarters, 1st Kentucky Brigade, Bowling Green, Kentucky, to Colonel Charles Dimmock, Chief of Ordnance, Richmond, Virginia, thanking him for muskets sent from Virginia to arm the 1st Kentucky., 1 leaf, negative photostats.
- Letter, 10 February 1867, from John B. Gordon, Brunswick, [Georgia], to J. William Jones, Goshen Bridge, [Rockbridge County], Virginia, asking for information on the war to be used in a biographical sketch of Gordon by E. A. Pollard., 1 leaf, negative photostats.
- Letter, 8 February 1875, from Joseph E. Johnston, Savannah, Georgia, to J. William Jones discussing his relationship with Robert E. Lee., 2 leaves, negative photostats.
- Letter, 10 May 1876, from Jefferson Davis, New Orleans, Louisiana, to J. William Jones commenting on allegations that he and the Confederate government had a hand in planning the assassination of Abraham Lincoln. Davis also deplores rhetorical attacks on the South., 3 leaves, negative photostats.
- Letter, 6 August 1876, from Johnn B. Hood, Alleghany Springs, Virginia, to J. William Jones asking Jones to send a review of a book.., 1 leaf, negative photostats.
- Letter, 23 July 1879, from Fitzhugh Lee, Richland, Stafford County, Virginia, to J. William Jones, Richmond, Virginia, asking Jones for the return of a letter., 1 leaf, negative photostats.
- Letter, 9 April 1883, from Jefferson Davis, Beauvoir, Mississippi, to J. William Jones concerning his role in a ceremony in which a statue of Robert E. Lee will be unveiled., 2 leaves, negative photostats.
- Letter, 10 August 1883, from Fitzhugh Lee, near Alexandria, Virginia, to J. William Jones concering a controversy between Lee and the Southern Historical Society over speaking fees., 2 leaves, negative photostats.
- Letter, 4 September 1883, from Fitzhugh Lee, near Alexandria, to J. William Jones, concering Jones' writing and Lee's dispute with the Southern Historical Society., 1 leaf, negative photostats.
- Letter, 8 January 1885, from Robert Stiles to J. William Jones with an enclosure, 7 January 1885, from Joseph E. Johnston to Stiles concerning the battle of Seven Pines [Fair Oaks] and Johnston's report of the battle., 2 leaves, negative photostats.
- Letter, 7 January 1887, Fitzhugh Lee, Richmond, to H. Douglas Lee, New York, New York, stating that he does not have an authograph of Jefferson Davis to give H. Douglas Lee and suggesting Lee contact Jones for one., 1 leaf, negative photostats.
- Letter, 18 July 1888, from Jefferson Davis, Beauvoir, to J. William Jones with enclosure, 13 July 1888, from J. B. Gambrell to Jefferson Davis, both discussing Davis' views on prohibition., 2 leaves, negative photostats.
- Letter, 29 July 1888, from Jefferson Davis, Beauvoir, to J. William Jones concerning his views on prohibition., 2 leaves, negative photostats.
- Letter, 30 August 1892, from Thomas Nelson Page, Richmond, to J. William Jones, Atlanta, Georgia, thanking Jones for his note and remarks on his books. Page is interested in seeing Jones' paper concerning African American education., 1 leaf, negative photostats.
- Letter, n.d., from Fitzhugh Lee, Alexandria, to J. William Jones regarding his dispute with the Southern Historical Society., 4 leaves, negative photostats.
- Letter, 2 February n.y., from John B. Gordon, Washington, D.C., to J. William Jones, Richmond, agreeing to write a letter of recommendation for someone., 1 leaf, negative photostats.
- Letter, n.d., from Winfield Scott to Major Edward [?] Johnson inviting him to dine with Scott and other guests., 1 leaf, negative photostats.